<!--
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Aidenkrz <aiden@djkraz.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2024 Kira Gbedan <161087999+Verbalase@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Aiden <28298836+Aidenkrz@users.noreply.github.com>
SPDX-FileCopyrightText: 2025 Rouge2t7 <81053047+Sarahon@users.noreply.github.com>

SPDX-License-Identifier: AGPL-3.0-or-later
-->

<Document>
  # Space Law
  The charter of corporate rights grants the following rights to Nanotrasen Employees, in order of importance.

  1. The right to follow corporate law.
  2. The right to work towards the greater wealth and prosperity of Nanotrasen.
  3. The right to respect one’s superiors in management and understand the hard work they accomplished to achieve their position.
  4. The right to a Nanotrasen appointed public defender. If no lawyer is currently available, then the security officer who arrested the employee will be appointed as their defender.
  5. The right to not be prosecuted under a § 01 offence. This right is waived if the party fails to comply with lawful orders from security officers that resolves this offence.

  ## Treatment Of Prisoners

  The charter of corporate rights grants the following rights to Nanotrasen Prisoners, in order of importance.

  1. The right to medical treatment.
  2. The right to communcations equipment, if not abused.
  3. The right to food and water.
  4. The right to their shift mandated PDA, unless tampered with; in which case a replacement will be issued.
  5. The right to freedom of movement within the designated brig.

  ## Security

  The charter of corporate rights grants the following rights to Security Employees, in order of importance.

  1. The right to search employees posessions on blue or higher alert, and to secure any contraband.
  2. The right to search employees suspected of a crime on any alert, and to secure any contraband.
  3. The right to check and remove any suspected illegal implants from crewmates suspected of possessing one.
  4. The right to implant any crewmate convicted of any crime with tracking and/or mindshield implants.
  5. The right to execute any crewmate refusing a mindshield implant.
  6. The right to waive brig time for corporal punishment, not exceeding critical condition.

  ## Sentencing

  The charter of corporate rights grants the following rights to the Warden, Head of Security, and in their absense other security employees.

  1. The right to sentence crewmates convicted of a crime for an appropriate time in the brig.
  2. The right to extend brig times for trouble caused.
  3. The right to use corporal punishment to retaliate against trouble caused.
  4. The right to the responsibility to preserve the life of all captured terrorists, magic users, and alien creatures for study at centcom.

  ## [color=red][bold]"YOU MAY NOT EXCEED 5 MINUTES AS A BRIG TIME"[/bold][/color]

  ## Any total brig time that adds up to above 5 minutes will be shortened to meet this limit.

  ## If it goes above 20 minutes, you may perma the person.

  # Crimes

  # I. Criminal Violations Title (Law Section, Code C0X-YY)

  ### Criminal violations are those that involve the employee themselves becoming classified as a criminal of some kind through their actions. Criminal violations encompass misdemeanours, felonies and taboo violations, these are the only actual laws that security cadets are expected to learn and remember, and should be prioritized.

  ## C§ 01 - No Penalty Misdemeanours:

  C§ 01 encompasses minor violations that are not considered indictable offences, punishment includes, but is not limited to; verbal warnings, citations, fines, as well as the offending party resolving the issue.

  - C01-01: Minor Contraband Possession; Having any item classified as contraband, that does not fall under any other codes. This includes, but is not limited to: departmentally-restricted contraband, rival corporate paraphernalia, and any item that does not fall under any other sections or codes.
  - C01-02: Littering; The improper disposal of waste via public dumping. This usually doesn't involve any sentence other than cleaning up the litter.
  - C01-03: Public Nuisance; The disorderly conduct of an employee in a public area that is disruptive to the work of other employees, or otherwise damages the Nanotrasen™ brand.
  - C01-04: Unsanctioned Assembly; Rallying a group of employees for unlawful reasons, including but not limited to: protests, riots, disruption of departments, organised criminal activity.
  - C01-05: Harassment; The act of intentionally offending, verbally intimidating or humiliating another employee.
  - C01-06: Dereliction of duty; The willful neglect of one's job duties.
  - C01-07: Trespass; The act of entering an area one does not have access to through non-forceful means and without explicit approval from a member of that department. Heads of staff reserve the right to waive any approvals given by members of their department.
  - C01-08: Unauthorized Use of Company Property; Using company property without explicit approval from a member of the department that the property belongs to. Heads of staff reserve the right to waive any approvals given by members of their department.
  - C01-09: Public Intoxication; The act of being intoxicated outside of designated hospitality areas such as bars, breakrooms, theaters, cafeterias or medbay if undergoing sobering treatment.
  - C01-10: Public Smoking and Vaping; The act of smoking or vaping outside of designated hospitality areas such as bars, breakrooms, theaters, cafeterias or offices.
  - C01-11: Departmental Impersonation; The act of wearing a departmental uniform whilst not being a part of that department.
  - C01-12: Vandalism; The act of intentionally defacing company property.
  - C01-13: Concealment of Identity; The act of intentionally hiding one's identity through the use of masks, disguises, failing to show company-mandated ID/PDA.
  - C01-14: Possession of Schedule A Narcotics; The act of possessing prohibited Schedule A narcotics.

  ## C§ 02 - Indictable Misdemeanours:

  C§ 02 encompasses minor violations that are indictable offences, punishment includes: incarceration, fines, corporal punishment or community service. The maximum sentence for C§ 02 incarceration is 3 minutes, if multiple C§ 02 violations have been committed the sentence may be increased to 5 minutes.

  - C02-01: Noncompliance; The act of refusing to comply with a lawful order from a security officer, or any order that resolves a C§ 01 offence.
  - C02-02: Battery; The act of intentionally causing physical harm to another employee.
  - C02-03: Assault; The act of threatening an employee with immediate physical harm.
  - C02-04: Petty Larceny; The act of stealing any item that does not belong to the offender. That does not fall under any other sections or codes.
  - C02-05: Burglary; The act of unlawfully entering an area one does not have access to through forceful means and with the intent to steal.
  - C02-06: Receiving and Handling Stolen Goods; The act of receiving or handling items that have been stolen knowingly.
  - C02-07: Breaking and Entering; The act of unlawfully entering an area one does not have access to through forceful means.
  - C02-08: Tampering; The act of intentionally sabotaging or interfering with company property or electronic systems.
  - C02-09: Bribery; The act of offering or accepting a bribe, which is any item, favor, or service offered in exchange for an illicit advantage.
  - C02-10: Possession of Prohibited Weaponry; The act of possessing prohibited weaponry that does not fall under any other sections or codes.
  - C02-11: Incitement of Violence; The act of encouraging or threatening violence against another employee, group of employees or department.
  - C02-12: Inciting a Riot; The act of organizing or causing a riot or unlawful assembly.
  - C02-13: Reckless Endangerment; The act of endangering the safety of other employees through reckless actions or inaction.
  - C02-14: Possession of Schedule B Narcotics; The act of possessing prohibited Schedule B narcotics.
  - C02-15: Conspiracy; The act of forming an agreement with other employees to commit a crime.
  - C02-16: Aiding and Abetting; The act of assisting in the commission of a crime, or providing support to those committing a crime.
  - C02-17: Evasion; The act of fleeing or failing to stop when being pursued or hailed by security, without using force.
  - C02-18: Obstruction of Work; The act of interfering with other employee's ability to work through forceful means, or otherwise impeding the work of other employees.
  - C02-19: Destruction of Property; The act of intentionally destroying company or personal property.

  ## C§ 03 - Indictable Felonies:

  C§ 03 encompasses serious violations that are indictable offences, punishment includes: incarceration, corporal punishment, community service and demotions. The maximum sentence for C§ 03 incarceration is 7 minutes, if multiple C§ 03 violations have been committed the sentence may be increased to 9 minutes, if the offending party consents they may accept a beating to reduce the sentence by 2 minutes.

  - C03-01: Secure Trespass; The act of entering a command or security area one does not have access to without explicit approval from a member of that department.
  - C03-02: Aggravated Battery; The act of intentionally causing physical harm to another employee by using a weapon or with the intent to cause serious bodily harm or death.
  - C03-03: Aggravated Assault; The act of threatening an employee with immediate physical harm by using a weapon or with the intent to cause serious bodily harm or death.
  - C03-04: Grand Larceny; The act of stealing any unique or valuable item that does not belong to the offender, that does not fall under any other sections or codes.
  - C03-05: Grand Theft; Stealing any high value or importance item.
  - C03-06: Destruction of Property; This includes killing any of the station-wide "pets" without a good reason.
  - C03-07: Grand Assault; Any assault on a member of security, the captain, or the corporate liaison, whether the intent is to murder or not.
  - C03-08: Grand Battery; Any battery on a member of security, the captain, or the corporate liaison, whether the intent is to murder or not.
  - C03-09: Unlawful Imprisonment; The act of holding an individual against their will without a justifiable basis. This includes but is not limited to: kidnapping, false arrest, and misconduct regarding incarceration.
  - C03-10: Possession of Firearms; The act of possessing firearms without proper authorization.
  - C03-11: Manufacture of Prohibited Weaponry; The act of manufacturing firearms or other prohibited weapons without proper authorization, this includes growing illegal fauna such as gatfruits or capfruits.
  - C03-12: Manufacture of Narcotics; The act of producing Schedule A/B substances, this includes growing fauna with intent to create narcotics.
  - C03-13: Obstruction of Justice; The act of interfering with security's ability to work through forceful means, or otherwise impeding the work of officers.
  - C03-14: Resisting Arrest; The act of using force to resist arrest by security personnel.
  - C03-15: Vigilantism; The act of taking the law into one's own hand and neglecting their own duties to do such.
  - C03-16: Involuntary Manslaughter; The act of unintentionally causing the death of another employee through reckless actions or inaction.

  ## C§ 04 - Disposable Criminal Violations:

  ### C§ 04 encompasses serious violations that specifically void the rights and contract of an employee and result in the disposable classification.

  - C04-01: Homicide; The act of killing another employee, whether intentionally or unintentionally.
  - C04-02: Attempted Homicide; The act of attempting to kill another employee.
  - C04-03: Prevention of Revival; The act of intentionally stopping, preventing or hindering the revival process of a deceased employee that does not have a do not resuscitate order through any means. This includes, but is not limited to: removing a corpse from medbay, hiding corpses, removing the corpse's brain or core, turning suit sensors off or otherwise disabling them.
  - C04-04: Breach of Custody; The act of removing someone or onesself who has been arrested from a secure area with the intent to free them, or preventing a security officer from making an arrest.
  - C04-05: Embezzlement; The act of stealing money that was entrusted to one's care by the corporation, such as taking money from a request computer for personal use. Heads reserve the right to offer bonuses that do not exceed 300 spesos.
  - C04-06: Fraud; The act of intentionally deceiving others or the corporation for personal gain.
  - C04-07: Forgery; The act of creating a false document, signature, stamp or other imitation of an item of value used with the intent to deceive another employee or the corporation.
  - C04-08: Terrorism; The act of mass violence or destruction against the corporation for ideological or political purposes.
  - C04-09: Attempted Malicious Engine Sabotage; The act of attempting to sabotage the station's singularity or tesla engine to cause a station-wide catastrophe.
  - C04-10: Unionization: The act of conspiring with other employees to unionize, striking or asking for "workers rights", which are a violation of corporate rights.

  # II. Taboo Violations Act (Law Code TX)

  ### Those who engage in taboo violations open themself up to immediate execution by security.

  ### Security team members should strive to capture alive those who violate taboo for study.

  - T1: Usage of Magic: Demonstrating usage of magic or usage of a magical item.
  - T2: Possession of Psionic Capabilities: Being capable of powers that mimic magic through the mind itself.
  - T3: Possession of Illegal DNA Modification: Commonly known mutations include: magic organs, hulk mutations, ork mutations and other
  - T4: Malicious Engine Sabotage; The act of sabotaging the station's singularity or tesla engine to cause a station-wide catastrophe.

  # III. Protocol Violations Act (Law Code PX)

  ### Protocol violations are generally the least serious and least likely to be punished violations of corporate law.

  ### When and if they are punished is usually at the discretion of the Corporate Liaison, who may request an officer from the HoS to help enforce the punishment.

  - P1: Time Theft: Any extended use of company time for purposes other than productive work. This generally means spending 15 minutes or more doing things other than one's job-related duties. The typical punishment is having to repay this time through salvage work, or being placed on a work plan that involves direct supervision.
  - P2: Unsanctioned Social Gatherings:  Attending and organizing parties, weddings, funerals, ect, that have not been written off by management staff.

  # IV. Disciplinary Violations Act (Law Code DX)

  ### Disciplinary violations are those that may be enforced at the discretion of security personnel or management staff. The typical punishment for them is corporal punishment.

  - D1: Excessive Public Drunkenness: Those who show excessive public drunkenness through vomiting and slurring of words are assumed to be impeding their ability to work.
  - D2: Insubordination: Failure to follow instructions from one's superior is considered insubordination. Their head is allowed to institute corporal punishment through use of a batong to re-instill a sense of discipline within them. In the case of security officers being insubordinate to the Head of Security, insubordination is considered much more severe and additional actions may be taken at the Head of Security's discretion.
  - D3: Disrespecting Corporate Authority: Disrespecting either the company, or a security officer acting on behalf of the company, shall result in swift corporal punishment, as well as a public apology being made. If the employee refuses to apologize for their transgression, more serious punishments such as brig time may be enacted.
  - D4: Departmental Trespassing: Entering a department one does not have access to without explicit approval of a member of that department. Heads of staff can overrule any approvals given by members of their department.

  # V. Managerial Violations Act (Law Code SDX)

  ### These are violations specifically by management staff.

  - SD1: Managerial Incompetence: When a command member is deemed incompetent at their job by either a member of CentComm, or by a vote among the heads, they shall be immediately stripped of their head of staff equipment, banished to salvage-work, and considered a D-Class employee from then on.
  - SD2: Insanity: When a command member is deemed as acting "insane" rather than incompetent, such as engaging in excessively silly behavior, they shall be required to submit to either the psychologist or the Chief Medical Officer for a psychological evaluation. They may then either prescribe a treatment plan, have the head of staff committed to the brig, or perform a lobotomy and have them work in salvage.
  - SD3: Conspiracy: Conspiring against the captain to unlawfully seize power without a proper justification shall result in all command members involved being stripped of their head of staff equipment, banished to salvage-work, and considered D-Class employees.

  # VI. Work Contract Violations Act (Law Code WX)

  ### These are violations specific to workers who are not employees of Nanotrasen.
  ### This includes visitors, salvagers, and other foreign agents.
  ### Punishment is at the discretion of the officer who finds individuals in violation of the code.

  - W1: Fraternization: Socializing with actual Nanotrasen Employees.
  - W2: Corporate Espionage: Taking proprietary Nanotrasen technology. Contractors should be searched before they get on the shuttle.
  - W3. Solicitation: Offering services to an employee for spesos or favors outside the scope of their contract, such as a mercenary contractor offering to act as a bodyguard for a Nanotrasen employee.
  - W4. Poaching: Trying to get a Nanotrasen employee to join their company.

  # VII. Racketeering and Organized Crime Act (Law Section R§)

  ## R§ 01 - Racketeering Misdemeanours

  R§ 01 encompasses minor violations related to organized crime and other forms of racketeering, these are incarceratable offenses with a maximum sentece of 4 minutes.

  ## R§ 02 - Racketeering Felonies

  R§ 02 encompasses serious violations related to organized crime and other forms of racketeering, these are incarceratable offenses with a maximum sentece of 6 minutes.

  ## R§ 03 - Racketeering Terminations

  R§ 03 encompasses serious violations related to organized crime and other forms of racketeering, that specifically void the rights and contract of the employee and result in the dispoable classification.
</Document>
